A Guide to the Papers of the Norfolk United Community Fund 1923-1970
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
The Papers of the Norfolk United Community Fund 1923-1970
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 36
6 Hollinger Document Case and 5 oversize boxes.
Administrative Information
Access
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
On loan from Eugene Berres, Executive V.P. United Community Fund, May 1978.
Biographical/Historical Information
The United Community Fund (UCF) was founded in 1923. The UCF was started to serve as a fundraising organization for the social services agencies of Norfolk. Over the years the United Community Fund has come to be known by different names. The group started as the United Community Fund. During World War II, the group became known as the United War Fund. After the war, the group changed its name to the Norfolk United Fund, and then later the Norfolk Community Chest.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of the Norfolk United Community Fund date from 1923 to 1970. The collection contains information about the business of the group, budget and finances, member agencies, correspondence, newspaper clippings, and fundraising campaigns. The inventories of Volumes 2-5 of UCF business papers can be found in Appendices A-D of this finding aid.
Arrangement
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically within each series.
Organization
The collection is broken down into the following series: I: Business; II: Scrapbooks; and III: Miscellaneous.
Series I: Business, consists of four bound volumes of business related material dating from 1928 to 1953. There is also an index of the materials that were contained in Volume one, which dates from 1923-1928. This volume was returned to the UCF and is no longer in the collection. These bound volumes contain meeting minutes; budget reports; correspondence; proposed by-laws, constitution changes, and policies; requests for money from affiliated agencies; Board elections and resolutions, and other business material. In addition to everyday business, each volume contains information that is historically significant for its time. Volume two contains business concerning unemployment relief during the Depression and the Federal Relief Act as pertaining to Norfolk. It is also interesting to note the participation of 'colored' people in the fund and fund agencies during a time of segregation, and how the UCF dealt with this. Volume three includes material related to the United Community Fund financial crisis and reorganization in 1938. This volume also contains more issues regarding segregation. Volume four contains business related to World War II relief efforts. Volume five includes history of the United War Fund and information about its dissolution. Also contained in this volume is an outline of the National Retirement Plan of 1946.
Series II: Scrapbooks, consists of sixteen scrapbooks. The pages of two of these scrapbooks have been placed in folders due to the age and condition of the items. Scrapbooks date from 1938 to 1970. Although some papers, correspondence, and forms are included, most of the material in the scrapbooks is newspaper clippings. Topics include articles related to the Community Fund and its affiliated agencies; and fund drives. Other articles discuss youth recreation; women on the police force in the 1940s; child welfare and adoption; tuberculosis; polio; heart disease; controlling venereal disease in Norfolk; numbers rackets and raids; public housing; inflation and rising prices in 1948; capitalism; crime; women job seekers in 1952. Of particular historical note are the newspaper clippings surrounding World War II in the July 1943-1945 scrapbook and the clippings on integration and desegregation on the 1968-1970 scrapbook. There is also material in this last scrapbook on the East Ghent Project where this area was redeveloped.
Series III: Miscellaneous, is mostly comprised of Fundraising Campaign material and publicity from approximately the 1950s and 1960s. Much of the material is undated or where dated does not list the year. Additionally, there is background material on the organization, maps, a booklet on the Robert Fulton Monument Association, and newspaper clippings from 1959 and 1960.
Contents List
- Business
  - Inventory of Volume One, 1923-1928 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Volume Two: Norfolk Community Fund, 1929-1933 (Box Box 1)
  - Volume Three: Norfolk Community Fund, 1934-1938 (Box Box 2)
  - Volume Four: Norfolk Community Fund, United War Fund, 1939-1945 (Box Box 3)
  - Volume Five: Norfolk Community Fund, United War Fund, United Fund Community Chest, 1946-1953 (Box Box 4)
- Scrapbooks
  - Scrapbook (Papers): 1938 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook (Newspaper Clippings): 1938 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook (Newspaper Clippings) Part I: March-April 1941 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook Part II (Newspaper Clippings): March-April 1941 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook Part III (Printing): March-April 1941 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook Part IV (Mimeographing): March-April 1941 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook Part V (Letters): March-April 1941 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook 1: 1938 (Box Box 6)
  - Scrapbook 4: November 1941-July 1943 (Box Box 6)
  - Scrapbook 5: March 1966-February 1967 (Box Box 6)
  - Scrapbook 6: 1967 (Box Box 6)
  - Scrapbook 1: July 1943-1945 (Box Box 7)
  - Scrapbook 2: 1948 (Box Box 7)
  - Scrapbook 1: 1948 (Box Box 8)
  - Scrapbook 2: 1949 (Box Box 8)
  - Scrapbook 3: 1949 (Box Box 8)
  - Scrapbook 1: 1950 (Box Box 9)
  - Scrapbook 2: 1952 (Box Box 9)
  - Scrapbook 1: 1957-1958 (Box Box 10)
  - Scrapbook 2: 1958-1959 (Box Box 10)
  - Scrapbook 3: 1968-1970 (Box Box 10)
- Miscellaneous
  - Index to the Minutes of the United Community Fund (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Campaign Material I (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Campaign Material II (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Campaign Material III (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Campaign Material IV (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Campaign Material V (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Publicity Packet: 1950 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Maps (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Extracts from the Minutes and Report of The Robert Fulton Monument Association (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 9)
  - 1958-1959 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Clippings: 1959-1960 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 11)